<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[visualyze.it - online merchandizing data analysis]]></title>
  <link href="http://visualyze-it.github.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://visualyze-it.github.com/"/>
  <updated>2012-03-16T17:16:22+10:00</updated>
  <id>http://visualyze-it.github.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Your Name]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Data Mining for Merchandizing Intelligence]]></title>
    <link href="http://visualyze-it.github.com/blog/2012/03/15/dive-in-boots-and-all/"/>
    <updated>2012-03-15T17:04:00+10:00</updated>
    <id>http://visualyze-it.github.com/blog/2012/03/15/dive-in-boots-and-all</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Here at visualyze.it we have developed a really interesting data-set tracking the price history
of tens of thousands of products from high-end merchants like Barneys and Saks.  The
data covers apparel, jewelry, beauty products, homewares and food items.</p>

<p>This data gives us a unique ability to analyze trends across many different merchants and
brands, and I want to show a little of that to you.  Let&#8217;s talk about boots for men.</p>

<p><a href="http://visualyze-it.github.com/images/2012-03-15/mens_boots.png">
<img src="http://visualyze-it.github.com/images/2012-03-15/mens_boots.png" title="&#34;Mens Boots&#34;" alt="&#34;Mens Boots&#34;">
</a></p>

<p>The visualyze.it price history data tracks the price fluctuations of several hundred pairs of mens boots
available from the major high-end retailers.  The figure below shows a the raw individual
price vectors over December 2011 and January 2012.</p>

<p><a href="http://visualyze-it.github.com/images/2012-03-15/mens_boots_product_price_vectors.png">
<img src="http://visualyze-it.github.com/images/2012-03-15/mens_boots_product_price_vectors.png" title="&#34;Mens Boots - Prodduct Price Vectors&#34;" alt="&#34;Mens Boots - Prodduct Price Vectors&#34;">
</a></p>

<p>You can click on the graph to view it in full detail, but you know it&#8217;s still
pretty much impenetrable; I&#8217;m including it to give you feel
for the depth of the raw data set.  Even in this dense forest of data
it is obvious that something interesting is happening in the pre-Christmas period;
prices drop very suddenly.  A few of the most expensive items are discounted
3 successive times in December.</p>

<p>So let&#8217;s dig a little deeper and see what more we can learn by looking at the same
data, this time aggregated by brand.  The figure below charts the mean price price of
mens boots by brand over a full year.</p>

<p><a href="http://visualyze-it.github.com/images/2012-03-15/mens_boots_mean_price_by_brand.png">
<img src="http://visualyze-it.github.com/images/2012-03-15/mens_boots_mean_price_by_brand.png" title="&#34;Mens Boots - Price Trend by Brand&#34;" alt="&#34;Mens Boots - Price Trend by Brand&#34;">
</a></p>

<p>There are two things that spring out of this; that boot prices are highly stratified by brand, with top-end brands like Rick Owens, Ann Dumeulemeester and Bruno Cucinelli commanding double the price of their competitors, and that mens boots are fiercely discounted in the Christmas season.</p>

<p>The degree of discounting for the high-end brands is impressive - around 50% mean price drop.  It would
be interesting to compare this aggregated by merchant instead of brand, to see if specific merchants are
driving this discounting.  The following figure shows the mean price for a pair of mens boots at
a number of major retailers over the course of year.</p>

<p><a href="http://visualyze-it.github.com/images/2012-03-15/mens_boots_mean_price_by_merchant.png">
<img src="http://visualyze-it.github.com/images/2012-03-15/mens_boots_mean_price_by_merchant.png" title="&#34;Mens Boots - Mean Price by Merchant&#34;" alt="&#34;Mens Boots - Mean Price by Merchant&#34;">
</a></p>

<p>You can see here that the seasonal price variation for mens boots at Barneys and Dolce &amp; Gabbana are quite severe.  No so with Gorsuch, Saks and Park and Bond.</p>

<p>The Dolce &amp; Gabbana pricing is fairly interesting, and worthy of a bit more exploration.  This next figure is
a bit more complicated, but you&#8217;ve come this far, so stick with me.  For this figure I&#8217;ve included the entire stock
range from Dolce and Gabbana, not just mens boots.  Since we maintain a long-term price trajectory
on all of the products we track, we can compare the current price to the standard price, and directly compute
the discount rate at any point in time.
The graph below shows the number of products (reflected by the size of each circle) at each
discount rate over the course of the last year.</p>

<p><a href="http://visualyze-it.github.com/images/2012-03-15/dolce_gabbana_all_stock_discounting.png">
<img src="http://visualyze-it.github.com/images/2012-03-15/dolce_gabbana_all_stock_discounting.png" title="&#34;Dolce Gabanna - All Stock - Discounting&#34;" alt="&#34;Dolce Gabanna - All Stock - Discounting&#34;">
</a></p>

<p>This figure gives a really clear picture of the Dolce Gabanna pricing strategy;
in July 2011, the majority of stock items at Dolce Gabbana
were discounted to 60% of MSRP for a few weeks followed by a further reduction to 50% MSRP.  Prices
returned to normal with no discounting at all until the first week of December, when again most stock items were
reduced to 60% of MSRP, this time for several months.  During this time a small number of items were
reduced to 55% and 50% MRSP.  Finally in February most stock was reduced to 50% MSRP.  It is also
evident that the total number of stock items available has been severely reduced during February.</p>

<p>Cleary Dolce Gabbana appreciate the importance of inventory turnover!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
